JOE: Many autistic people will show signs
of distress before having a meltdown, this
is sometimes called the “rumble stage”.
They may start to exhibit signs
of anxiety like pacing or pacing,
rocking or becoming very still.
At this stage, there may still
be a chance to prevent a meltdown
happening, by using distraction,
diversion and calming strategies
and removing potential triggers.
BETH: It can help to identify the cause
of the potential meltdown as it is a
reaction to an overwhelming experience.
Recording what is happening before,
during and after each meltdown may
show patterns in its occurrence like
particular times, particular places, or
when something particular has happened.
Once a clearer idea of what may be
triggering meltdowns is more evident, ways
to minimise the triggers can be organised.
JOE: Every individual with
autism is different, but sensory
differences, changes in routine,
anxiety, and communication
difficulties are common triggers.
A meltdown happens when an individual
becomes completely overwhelmed by
their current situation and temporarily
loses control of their behaviour.
This can be expressed verbally
by shouting, screaming or crying.
It can also be expressed physically
by kicking, lashing out and biting,
or it could be expressed in both ways.
BETH: It is not bad or naughty
behaviour, like a temper tantrum, as the
individual is completely overwhelmed.
Their disorder means that it is difficult
to express their feelings in any other
way and the result is a meltdown.
JOE: Meltdowns are not the only
way however, that individuals
may express feeling overwhelmed.
They may withdraw from situations
and refuse to interact.
If someone is having a meltdown,
or not responding, they should be
given some time to recover from
information or sensory overload.
If they are in a public place,
they should be asked calmly if they
are OK and given time to respond.
Others should be kept away so
as not to cause more distress.
Sensory stimuli and information
overload should be reduced wherever
possible by taking them quietly
somewhere calmer and safer.
Strategies such as deep
breathing could also be used.
BETH: When they are in full meltdown
mode, they may lack the ability to be
reasoned with, redirected or distracted.
However, this level of agitation
does not just happen, it can be
anticipated and de-escalated.
It is important then to have a
plan for what to do in a crisis.
Details of events, triggers or signs
that a crisis situation might develop,
should be documented along with
tools and strategies for keeping the
individual and those around them safe.
JOE: Intervention steps and de-escalation
procedures related to each increasing
level of agitation, should be noted
and lists of things to do and not to
do according to the fears and needs of
the individual should be clearly shown.
Previous information from past episodes of
concern should be clearly indicated along
with information and contact details of
family, professionals or support who need
to be contacted in the event of a problem.